<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>news on GIS @ Harvard Libraries</title>
    <link>https://harvardmapcollection.github.io/tags/news/</link>
    <description>Recent content in news on GIS @ Harvard Libraries</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://harvardmapcollection.github.io/tags/news/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Introducing GIS Office Hours</title>
      <link>https://harvardmapcollection.github.io/posts/office-hours/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://harvardmapcollection.github.io/posts/office-hours/</guid>
      <description>Join us Spring 2023 for weekly GIS office hours. We will meet in the Lamont media lab annex every Tuesday from 10am-12pm.
What to expect Chat about GIS tools and datasets Meet others using GIS in their work Share projects and get feedback What office hours are not You don’t need to have a specific question! Just an interest. Depending on how many people we have, you may still need to book a personal consultation for more in-depth advice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How students have georeferenced our map collections</title>
      <link>https://harvardmapcollection.github.io/posts/voulgaris/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://harvardmapcollection.github.io/posts/voulgaris/</guid>
      <description>The course Earlier this Fall, we visited with Carole Voulgaris&amp;rsquo;s Spatial Analysis class from the Graduate School of Design.
Example georeferencing assignment submitted by GSD student Ellie Shield.
The assignments in Spatial Analysis are tailored to introduce fundamental geospatial competencies, as well as center group collaboration, creativity, and iterative design.
THE VISIT In early September 2021, The Harvard Map Collection facilitated a class visit with Spatial Analysis, where we discussed shifts in cartographic theory, introduced the map collection, and foreshadowed the concept of georeferencing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How graphics journalists approach digital mapping</title>
      <link>https://harvardmapcollection.github.io/posts/graphics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://harvardmapcollection.github.io/posts/graphics/</guid>
      <description>Skills to create beautiful and engaging maps can be strengthened in a semester, says Bloomberg graphics journalist.
The type of narrative, map-based digital projects we see in the news, like the recent CityLab project documenting racist urban infrastructure in St. Paul, Minnesota require many research and technical skills to pull off.
The Harvard Map Collection asked Bloomberg graphics journalist, Rachael Dottle about her methodology in scoping, researching, and creating maps for this story.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
