<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>news on GIS, maps &#43; data @ Harvard Libraries</title>
    <link>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/tags/news/</link>
    <description>Recent content in news on GIS, maps &#43; data @ Harvard Libraries</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/tags/news/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Preserving GIS research data for long-term discovery and access</title>
      <link>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/posts/odessa-biodiversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/posts/odessa-biodiversity/</guid>
      <description>Floral motif from Ukrainian textile produced in 1902.
This year, the Harvard Map Collection partnered with Kelly O&amp;rsquo;Neill from the Davis Center on a project to demonstrate the value of our GIS data curation services . Dr. O&amp;rsquo;Neill&amp;rsquo;s project aims to capture data about historic biodiversity in the Ukraine. The Harvard Map Collection worked with her team to co-develop robust and useful metadata, so that the sources can be archived for long-term discovery and reuse.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploratory data visualization of Harvard Geospatial Library collections</title>
      <link>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/posts/exploratory-hgl/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/posts/exploratory-hgl/</guid>
      <description>This summer, we were pleased to host two rising seniors, Vivian Nha Nguyen and Dhruv Chugh as May-Crane fellows . Vivian and Dhruv worked on a project to apply data analysis methodology from their coursework to a real-world corpus of data &amp;ndash; the over 11,000 metadata records for GIS datasets hosted in the Harvard Geospatial Library (HGL) .
We framed this project as a way to get a better sense of both the data hosted in HGL, as well as the way we collect and describe GIS data at Harvard Libraries.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disciplinary frames to working with data</title>
      <link>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/posts/data-disciplines/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/posts/data-disciplines/</guid>
      <description>One of the goals of this blog is to help you become better positioned in understanding the networks of research data services happening across the Harvard community. There is a lot of data research happening at Harvard. There are also lot of places to get help. In our GIS support services, we encounter a wide range of disciplinary backgrounds when we are helping researchers with their data. The software, methods, and conceptual approaches to working with data can vary greatly, depending on which school you are coming from.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publishing tips from a data safety expert</title>
      <link>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/posts/potterbusch/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/posts/potterbusch/</guid>
      <description>In this interview with Megan Potterbusch , the Harvard Kennedy School&amp;rsquo;s Research Data Steward, you will learn:
How to balance open science and data safety How to get started with support for your research The interview BELLE LIPTON: Megan, can you introduce us to your role?
MEGAN POTTERBUSCH: I work within the Kennedy School’s Libraries and Research Services. I’m the primary reviewer for data safety plans. A data safety plan is required for anyone who is working with regulated or contracted data, especially data that is considered sensitive.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Approaching language data mapping with GIS and D3.js</title>
      <link>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/posts/russian-language/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/posts/russian-language/</guid>
      <description>We met undergraduate Paige Lee while working with her general education class about how borders are constructed. In the class, students were asked to complete a project, choosing from a variety of format options, including making a map. The Harvard Map Collection supported students by advising on searching for data, using mapping software, and scoping out project ideas.
In this interview, we look at Paige’s custom-coded interactive mapping visualization, and learn more about her thought process and workflow.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing GIS Office Hours</title>
      <link>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/posts/office-hours/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/posts/office-hours/</guid>
      <description>Join us Spring 2023 for weekly GIS office hours. We will meet in the Lamont media lab annex every Tuesday from 10am-12pm.
What to expect Chat about GIS tools and datasets Meet others using GIS in their work Share projects and get feedback What office hours are not You don’t need to have a specific question! Just an interest. Depending on how many people we have, you may still need to book a personal consultation for more in-depth advice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning GIS while working in the map archives</title>
      <link>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/posts/mapping-cultural-difference/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/posts/mapping-cultural-difference/</guid>
      <description>This project was made possible through a May Crane fellowship .
Mapping Cultural Difference The goal of this webpage is to allow others to follow the progress of this mapping project and understand the immediate and long-term goals and uses of the mapping project.
About this mapping project At its inception, this project&amp;rsquo;s main goal is to demonstrate cultural distance and difference as they pertain to staged representations of Latinx (or Latine) Americans living in the United States.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Faculty designing GIS projects around map archives</title>
      <link>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/posts/voulgaris/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/posts/voulgaris/</guid>
      <description>Earlier this Fall, we visited with Carole Voulgaris&amp;rsquo;s Spatial Analysis class from the Graduate School of Design.
Example georeferencing assignment submitted by GSD student Ellie Shield.
The assignments in Spatial Analysis are tailored to introduce fundamental geospatial competencies, as well as center group collaboration, creativity, and iterative design.
THE VISIT In early September 2021, The Harvard Map Collection facilitated a class visit with Spatial Analysis, where we discussed shifts in cartographic theory, introduced the map collection, and foreshadowed the concept of georeferencing .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GIS storytelling tips from a professional graphics journalist</title>
      <link>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/posts/graphics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/posts/graphics/</guid>
      <description>Skills to create beautiful and engaging maps can be strengthened in a semester, says Bloomberg graphics journalist.
The type of narrative, map-based digital projects we see in the news, like the recent CityLab project documenting racist urban infrastructure in St. Paul, Minnesota require many research and technical skills to pull off.
The Harvard Map Collection asked Bloomberg graphics journalist, Rachael Dottle about her methodology in scoping, researching, and creating maps for this story.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
