<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Interview on GIS, maps &#43; data @ Harvard Library</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/interview/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Interview on GIS, maps &#43; data @ Harvard Library</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/interview/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Faces Behind the Data, Anna He and the Harvard Geospatial Library</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/faces-behind-the-data-anna-he/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/faces-behind-the-data-anna-he/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this interview, we get to know Anna He, the newest member in the Map Collection. Anna’s role is the Geospatial Data Technician for the Harvard Geospatial Library (HGL).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family:lorabold;color:#5f0217;&#34;&gt;BELLE LIPTON:&lt;/span&gt; What will your role be, related to the Harvard Geospatial Library (HGL)?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family:lorabold;color:#5f0217;&#34;&gt;ANNA HE:&lt;/span&gt; As a geospatial data technician for HGL, I help manage geospatial data and metadata production for the Harvard Geospatial Library, primarily on the back end. My day-to-day involves tasks like doing quality control of geospatial datasets to ensure accuracy and troubleshooting any metadata-related errors. This ensures that when Harvard community members—students and professors—want to use the data, they can download and use it smoothly without any issues.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Harvard&#39;s research data landscape</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/boyd/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/boyd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this interview, we are lucky to speak with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.iq.harvard.edu/people/ceilyn-boyd&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ceilyn Boyd&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;, the Dataverse Development Project Manager at Harvard’s Institute for Quantitative Social Science (IQSS). Prior to her role with IQSS, Ceilyn served as the Manager of the Harvard Library Research Data Management Program. In this interview, she provides an invaluable tour around the complex research data ecosystem of Harvard University.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family:lorabold;color:#5f0217;&#34;&gt;BELLE LIPTON:&lt;/span&gt; Hi Ceilyn. Thank you for speaking with us. We believe you are the ideal person to explain research data services at Harvard, given your experience working with the libraries in a data services role and your current position with Harvard Dataverse. During your time at the library, you conducted thorough assessments of the many services offered to researchers. Could you help us define “data services” for our readers, do you have an elevator pitch?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Publishing tips from a data safety expert</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/potterbusch/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/potterbusch/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this interview with &lt;a href=&#34;https://library.harvard.edu/staff/megan-potterbusch&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Megan Potterbusch&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;, the Harvard Kennedy School&amp;rsquo;s Research Data Steward, you will learn:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;How to balance open science and data safety&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;How to get started with support for your research&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-interview&#34;&gt;The interview&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family:lorabold;color:#5f0217;&#34;&gt;BELLE LIPTON:&lt;/span&gt; Megan, can you introduce us to your role?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family:lorabold;color:#5f0217;&#34;&gt;MEGAN POTTERBUSCH:&lt;/span&gt; I work within the Kennedy School’s Libraries and Research Services. I’m the primary reviewer for data safety plans. A data safety plan is required for anyone who is working with regulated or contracted data, especially data that is considered sensitive. That means if there is a data use agreement, a licensing agreement, special terms of use, or an IRB, there are paths into the data safety system. It’s unusual for a librarian to serve in this capacity because it usually falls under a School Security Officer or something like that. Here at Harvard Kennedy School, I serve in that role because it’s all about Research Data Management.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interview with graphics journalist, Rachael Dottle</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/graphics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/graphics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p class=&#34;callout&#34;&gt;Skills to create beautiful and engaging maps can be strengthened in a semester, says Bloomberg graphics journalist.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The type of narrative, map-based digital projects we see in the news, like the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/graphics/2021-urban-highways-infrastructure-racism/?cmpid=BBD072821_CITYLAB&amp;amp;utm_medium=email&amp;amp;utm_source=newsletter&amp;amp;utm_term=210728&amp;amp;utm_campaign=citylabdaily&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;recent CityLab project documenting racist urban infrastructure in St. Paul, Minnesota&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; require many research and technical skills to pull off.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Harvard Map Collection asked Bloomberg graphics journalist, &lt;a href=&#34;https://rachaeldottle.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rachael Dottle&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; about her methodology in scoping, researching, and creating maps for this story.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
