<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on GIS, maps &#43; data @ Harvard Library</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/projects/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on GIS, maps &#43; data @ Harvard Library</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Vectorizing Historic Maps for Spatial Analysis</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/projects/adler/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/projects/adler/</guid>
      <description>Generating Geospatial Data from Historic Maps: A Step-by-Step Guide This project illustrates a core methodology supported by the Harvard Map Collection: transforming static historic maps into analyzable geospatial data. Through our partnership with Joyce Chaplin&amp;#39;s &amp;#39;Re-Wilding Harvard&amp;#39; course, this initiative empowered students to investigate the evolving histories and changing natures of open space within Harvard&amp;#39;s campus and its surroundings, showcasing the library&amp;#39;s critical role in digital scholarship.&#xA;Hannah Adler &amp;#39;25, a student from the course, undertook an ambitious project focusing on the Charles River region of Harvard&amp;#39;s campus, particularly the area near Memorial Drive in Cambridge.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A GIS database and webmap of historic Black life on Boston&#39;s Beacon Hill</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/projects/mapping-black-boston/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/projects/mapping-black-boston/</guid>
      <description>This is a prototype for Mapping Black Boston, a research project by David Weimer. Dave, our former Map Librarian, is now Curator of Maps and Director of the Center for the History of Cartography at the Newberry Library. For information on the project, or to collaborate, you can get in touch with Dave .&#xA;Check out the interactive Mapping Black Boston prototype .&#xA;To access the underlying project data, visit the project Github .</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
