<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on GIS, maps &#43; data @ Harvard Library</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on GIS, maps &#43; data @ Harvard Library</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Dive into the Putumayo &#34;World Music&#34; archive</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/putumayo/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/putumayo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We met Natalia Neira Nieto, a G1 in the Music Department&amp;rsquo;s Ethnomusicology program this summer when she was completing work for a library fellowship. Natalia&amp;rsquo;s work this summer was focused on wrangling geographic data about an important recording collection held in the Harvard Eda Kuhn Loeb Music Library.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Natalia&amp;rsquo;s project, in addition to exploring the subject matter related to her area of study, ethomusicology, uncovered many insights about the complexities and real-world impact that decision making within data projects can entail. Her work perfectly encapsulates what one can expect when embarking on a thoughtfully-scoped data project. We are happy to share her reflections.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Faces Behind the Data, Anna He and the Harvard Geospatial Library</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/faces-behind-the-data-anna-he/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/faces-behind-the-data-anna-he/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this interview, we get to know Anna He, the newest member in the Map Collection. Anna’s role is the Geospatial Data Technician for the Harvard Geospatial Library (HGL).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family:lorabold;color:#5f0217;&#34;&gt;BELLE LIPTON:&lt;/span&gt; What will your role be, related to the Harvard Geospatial Library (HGL)?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family:lorabold;color:#5f0217;&#34;&gt;ANNA HE:&lt;/span&gt; As a geospatial data technician for HGL, I help manage geospatial data and metadata production for the Harvard Geospatial Library, primarily on the back end. My day-to-day involves tasks like doing quality control of geospatial datasets to ensure accuracy and troubleshooting any metadata-related errors. This ensures that when Harvard community members—students and professors—want to use the data, they can download and use it smoothly without any issues.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mapping Land Use Change in the Sacramento San-Joaquin River Delta</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/adler-delta/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/adler-delta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Early one August morning, I found myself donning borrowed fishing waders on the banks of a restored tidal wetland in Northern California. Thanks to a Salata Institute grant, I spent a week studying the Sacramento San-Joaquin River Delta alongside biometeorology experts. After exploring maps of the region through my assistantship with the Harvard Map Collection, I was incredibly grateful for the opportunity to traverse the landscape on foot, and prepare for my senior thesis on the science of these special ecosystems. In broad terms, I&amp;rsquo;m interested in wetlands — swamps, marshes, sloughs, estuaries — and how they exchange carbon dioxide and methane with the atmosphere. GIS and historic maps allow me to track wetlands over time and estimate historic data related to this gas exchange. The following article explores how wetlands are related to global warming, the relationship between land-use and greenhouse gasses, and what a century-old map can teach us about climate change.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Geographical Cat in the Box, a remembered yet unknown Institute of Geographical Exploration at Harvard (1930-1951)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/nicolae/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/nicolae/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This dataset and story open the past of Harvard University’s &lt;em&gt;Institute of Geographical Exploration&lt;/em&gt; (HUIGE, 1930-1951). The HUIGE was a building, a branch of Harvard’s defunct Geography department, a home to many students, and still a mystery to this day.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The scope of this project is simple: making &lt;a href=&#34;https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/projects/huige/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;a guide&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; to as many repositories of HUIGE-related artifacts across Harvard’s campus and other institutions across Massachusetts.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;This guide cannot be complete but will hopefully help launch further inquiries into the fate of Aerial Photography and Geography at Harvard and in the USA.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The hope of this project is to call to action anyone with further knowledge about the HUIGE, its activities, and the evolving role of Aerial Photography between WWI and the evolution of Satellite Imagery in order to complete the gaps hinted at in this story.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;This project was supported by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://library.harvard.edu/grants-fellowships/pforzheimer-fellowships&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Pforzheimer Fellowship&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; at Harvard, with a focus on Geospatial Data and Archival Research, and overseen by the Map Collections and especially Belle Lipton.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Every good story starts with a spark and a helping hand to fan it. This one stems from the records and institutional knowledge unveiled by the wonderful people at Havard’s Map Collection. Custodians of many important maps and the personal documents of geographers having worked at Harvard, our Map librarians have kept a finger on the pulse of Geography’s unravelling at Harvard and beyond. Due to their unrestrained support, I was brought in contact in the very beginning of my Pforzheimer Fellowship with four inestimable pillars of the HUIGE’s story:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Off the Beaten Path?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/off-the-beaten-path/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/off-the-beaten-path/</guid>
      <description>&lt;video width=&#34;100%&#34;  controls&gt;&#xA;  &lt;source src=&#34;media/Off the beaten path.mp4&#34; type=&#34;video/mp4&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;/video&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When I first arrived in Boston three years ago, only a few weeks away from starting college in the heart of Cambridge, I wanted to take in as much of the city as I could. Armed with a TripAdvisor list of &amp;ldquo;The 10 Best Things to Do in Boston&amp;rdquo; and a confusing MBTA map I found at the airport, I set off to the city&amp;rsquo;s tourists hotspots, historical landmarks, and buzzing restaurants. As one often does, I walked the Freedom Trail, shopped at Newbury Street, ate at a nice Back Bay restaurant, and bought an overpriced Red Sox cap at the Commons. By the time I checked everything off my list and felt comfortable taking the T without a map, I thought I knew what I had to know about the city. Needless to say, I was wrong.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Re-Wilding Harvard, Spring 2024</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/re-wilding-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/re-wilding-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During Spring 2024, the Harvard Map Collection embedded with history course Re-Wilding Harvard, taught by Professor Joyce Chaplin. From the syllabus, &amp;ldquo;re-wilding returns a place to an earlier form to promote biodiversity; urban re-wilding does this within urban spaces, including Harvard’s.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;media/re-wild.png&#34; alt=&#34;Planter at Harvard Museum of Natural History&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.harvardmagazine.com/2022/08/re-wilding-harvard&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Re-wilded site&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; from 2021, at the Harvard Museum of Natural History.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In past iterations of the course, students studied historic dimensions of pre-colonial landscapes and ecosystems at Harvard and their impact on what exists now. Students have even re-wilded two sites, one at the Museum of Natural History, and another at the Business School. Throughout this learning, maps played a role in helping to understand places on campus, past and present. When Professor Chaplin and I met during a visit to the Map Collection in 2022, she was interested in the potential for beginning to introduce GIS in class, so students could engage more deeply with these topics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mapping Black Cambridge</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mapping-black-cambridge/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mapping-black-cambridge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Harvard Map Collection recently partnered with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.leventhalmap.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Leventhal Map and Education Center&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; at the&#xA;Boston Public Library to support a digital mapping project by scholars Joan Brunetta and Eve Loftus. Joan and Eve&amp;rsquo;s project, titled &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.leventhalmap.org/articles/mapping-black-cambridge/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mapping Black Cambridge&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;, contributes to an evolving landscape of available data used to discern historic dimensions of Black life in Boston and Cambridge.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;media/1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Old archives&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Leveraging historic maps and records from local libraries and archives, along with &lt;a href=&#34;https://library.harvard.edu/libraries/harvard-map-collection#spatial&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GIS training services&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;, Joan and Eve have created a dataset from their meticulous research about Black life in Cambridge in the 19th century. Researchers can now browse Joan and Eve&amp;rsquo;s findings in an &lt;a href=&#34;https://felt.com/map/Mapping-Black-Cambridge-1790-1820-Snapshots-from-the-First-Four-Federal-Censuses-ghIMa0VXTy6XhXh9A1g2bhA?loc=42.36999,-71.09789,12.89z&amp;amp;share=1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;interactive web map&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Harvard&#39;s research data landscape</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/boyd/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/boyd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this interview, we are lucky to speak with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.iq.harvard.edu/people/ceilyn-boyd&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ceilyn Boyd&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;, the Dataverse Development Project Manager at Harvard’s Institute for Quantitative Social Science (IQSS). Prior to her role with IQSS, Ceilyn served as the Manager of the Harvard Library Research Data Management Program. In this interview, she provides an invaluable tour around the complex research data ecosystem of Harvard University.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family:lorabold;color:#5f0217;&#34;&gt;BELLE LIPTON:&lt;/span&gt; Hi Ceilyn. Thank you for speaking with us. We believe you are the ideal person to explain research data services at Harvard, given your experience working with the libraries in a data services role and your current position with Harvard Dataverse. During your time at the library, you conducted thorough assessments of the many services offered to researchers. Could you help us define “data services” for our readers, do you have an elevator pitch?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Undoing Empire, One Plant at a Time</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/odessa-biodiversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/odessa-biodiversity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;media/picture.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Old picture of flowers&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;em&gt;Floral motif from Ukrainian textile produced in 1902.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This year, the Harvard Map Collection partnered with Kelly O&amp;rsquo;Neill from the Davis Center on a project to demonstrate the value of our &lt;a href=&#34;https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/resources/researchers-handbook/long-term-preservation/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GIS data curation services&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;. Dr. O&amp;rsquo;Neill&amp;rsquo;s project aims to capture data about historic biodiversity in the Ukraine. The Harvard Map Collection worked with her team to co-develop robust and useful metadata, so that the sources can be archived for long-term discovery and reuse.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Publishing tips from a data safety expert</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/potterbusch/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/potterbusch/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this interview with &lt;a href=&#34;https://library.harvard.edu/staff/megan-potterbusch&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Megan Potterbusch&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;, the Harvard Kennedy School&amp;rsquo;s Research Data Steward, you will learn:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;How to balance open science and data safety&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;How to get started with support for your research&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-interview&#34;&gt;The interview&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family:lorabold;color:#5f0217;&#34;&gt;BELLE LIPTON:&lt;/span&gt; Megan, can you introduce us to your role?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family:lorabold;color:#5f0217;&#34;&gt;MEGAN POTTERBUSCH:&lt;/span&gt; I work within the Kennedy School’s Libraries and Research Services. I’m the primary reviewer for data safety plans. A data safety plan is required for anyone who is working with regulated or contracted data, especially data that is considered sensitive. That means if there is a data use agreement, a licensing agreement, special terms of use, or an IRB, there are paths into the data safety system. It’s unusual for a librarian to serve in this capacity because it usually falls under a School Security Officer or something like that. Here at Harvard Kennedy School, I serve in that role because it’s all about Research Data Management.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mapping the Russian Language</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/russian-language/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/russian-language/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We met undergraduate Paige Lee while working with her general education class about how borders are constructed. In the class, students were asked to complete a project, choosing from a variety of format options, including making a map. The Harvard Map Collection supported students by advising on searching for data, using mapping software, and scoping out project ideas.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this interview, we look at Paige’s custom-coded interactive mapping visualization, and learn more about her thought process and workflow.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>City Fictions</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/city-fictions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/city-fictions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This semester, we worked with &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.harvard.edu/gazette/story/2021/10/harvard-scholar-elucidates-the-power-of-literary-voices/&#34;&gt;Tara K. Menon&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; English class, titled City Fictions. In this class, undergraduates explored the various ways writers capture the constituent features of life in urban environments, reading books set in London, Bombay, New York, and Tokyo.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;img-zoom-a-little&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;img src=&#34;media/2.png&#34; style=&#34;width:100%; max-height:70em;&#34; alt=&#34;Screencapture of Map of London from 1914.&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/ids:49970081&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Wonderground map of the London town, 1914.&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We were happy to learn that one of the course assignments involved mapmaking; in order to get at different ways the experience of city might be represented, students were tasked with creating two distinct maps of the same place.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interview with graphics journalist, Rachael Dottle</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/graphics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/graphics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p class=&#34;callout&#34;&gt;Skills to create beautiful and engaging maps can be strengthened in a semester, says Bloomberg graphics journalist.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The type of narrative, map-based digital projects we see in the news, like the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/graphics/2021-urban-highways-infrastructure-racism/?cmpid=BBD072821_CITYLAB&amp;amp;utm_medium=email&amp;amp;utm_source=newsletter&amp;amp;utm_term=210728&amp;amp;utm_campaign=citylabdaily&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;recent CityLab project documenting racist urban infrastructure in St. Paul, Minnesota&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; require many research and technical skills to pull off.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Harvard Map Collection asked Bloomberg graphics journalist, &lt;a href=&#34;https://rachaeldottle.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rachael Dottle&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; about her methodology in scoping, researching, and creating maps for this story.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
