<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>census on GIS, maps &#43; data @ Harvard Library</title>
    <link>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/tags/census/</link>
    <description>Recent content in census on GIS, maps &#43; data @ Harvard Library</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/tags/census/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Census series introduction</title>
      <link>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/tutorials/census-data-primer/introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/tutorials/census-data-primer/introduction/</guid>
      <description>The census series will equip you with all of the skills necessary to work with census data for digital mapping.
The United States census is a huge topic, and you may or may not have worked with census data before.
Being able to navigate census data GIS files, and handle them in a way compatible with digital mapping is not intuitive, and this tutorial series is designed to set you up to be confident making census maps with GIS.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Download census data for GIS</title>
      <link>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/tutorials/census-data-primer/download-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/tutorials/census-data-primer/download-data/</guid>
      <description>Example data We will be exploring tenure data, which looks at owner vs. renter-occupied units. We want census responses that have been aggregated to the census tract level. Our area of study is near the Harvard campus, in Somerville and Cambridge. We&amp;rsquo;ll be looking at the most recent estimates at the time this guide was written, 2015-2019. Geography tip: Census tracts are a popular aggregation unit, as they are more granular than county or state level data, but more available and statistically-reliable than block level data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Perform a table join in QGIS</title>
      <link>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/tutorials/census-data-primer/perform-a-table-join/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/tutorials/census-data-primer/perform-a-table-join/</guid>
      <description>Need help turning your spreadsheet data into a map? In this tutorial you will learn how to join tables to GIS shapefiles to create a new, mappable dataset with both geographic boundaries and statistical or attribute information.
Why do we join? Often, spreadsheets contain useful information we want to map. GIS software, however, does not know how to translate a spreadsheet without any inherent spatial information (such as point coordinates) into a visual map.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clip a dataset in QGIS</title>
      <link>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/tutorials/census-data-primer/clip-a-dataset/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/tutorials/census-data-primer/clip-a-dataset/</guid>
      <description>Clipping is a way of cropping GIS data to a certain extent.
1
Why do we clip? Large datasets can be unwieldy and difficult to work with. You can create more effective visualizations if your data is focused. Tutorial data In this tutorial you will clip a shapefile of all census tracts in the United States to create a new shapefile of only census tracts in Cambridge, Massachusetts. For those who are following the census data tutorial series , we will be using the United States Census Tracts file we just created.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Normalize data in QGIS</title>
      <link>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/tutorials/census-data-primer/normalize-a-dataset/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/tutorials/census-data-primer/normalize-a-dataset/</guid>
      <description>Ensure your dataset is prepared in a way that permits you to make clear and responsible arguments when you are mapping. To cover your bases, read through this guide on statistical mapping best practices .
In this tutorial, we will cover one common data cleaning task &amp;ndash; that of &amp;ldquo;normalizing&amp;rdquo; data.
&amp;ldquo;To normalize, in a statistical sense, is to transform a set of measurements so that they may be compared in a meaningful way.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
