<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Research Story on GIS, maps &#43; data @ Harvard Library</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/research-story/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Research Story on GIS, maps &#43; data @ Harvard Library</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/research-story/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A Geographical Cat in the Box, a remembered yet unknown Institute of Geographical Exploration at Harvard (1930-1951)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/nicolae/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/nicolae/</guid>
      <description>This dataset and story open the past of Harvard University’s Institute of Geographical Exploration (HUIGE, 1930-1951). The HUIGE was a building, a branch of Harvard’s defunct Geography department, a home to many students, and still a mystery to this day.&#xA;The scope of this project is simple: making a guide to as many repositories of HUIGE-related artifacts across Harvard’s campus and other institutions across Massachusetts. This guide cannot be complete but will hopefully help launch further inquiries into the fate of Aerial Photography and Geography at Harvard and in the USA.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mapping Black Cambridge</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mapping-black-cambridge/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mapping-black-cambridge/</guid>
      <description>The Harvard Map Collection recently partnered with the Leventhal Map and Education Center at the Boston Public Library to support a digital mapping project by scholars Joan Brunetta and Eve Loftus. Joan and Eve&amp;rsquo;s project, titled Mapping Black Cambridge , contributes to an evolving landscape of available data used to discern historic dimensions of Black life in Boston and Cambridge.&#xA;Leveraging historic maps and records from local libraries and archives, along with GIS training services , Joan and Eve have created a dataset from their meticulous research about Black life in Cambridge in the 19th century.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
