<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Research Story on GIS, maps &#43; data @ Harvard Library</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/research-story/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Research Story on GIS, maps &#43; data @ Harvard Library</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/research-story/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A Geographical Cat in the Box, a remembered yet unknown Institute of Geographical Exploration at Harvard (1930-1951)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/nicolae/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/nicolae/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This dataset and story open the past of Harvard University’s &lt;em&gt;Institute of Geographical Exploration&lt;/em&gt; (HUIGE, 1930-1951). The HUIGE was a building, a branch of Harvard’s defunct Geography department, a home to many students, and still a mystery to this day.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The scope of this project is simple: making &lt;a href=&#34;https://mapping.share.library.harvard.edu/projects/huige/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;a guide&lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA; to as many repositories of HUIGE-related artifacts across Harvard’s campus and other institutions across Massachusetts.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;This guide cannot be complete but will hopefully help launch further inquiries into the fate of Aerial Photography and Geography at Harvard and in the USA.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The hope of this project is to call to action anyone with further knowledge about the HUIGE, its activities, and the evolving role of Aerial Photography between WWI and the evolution of Satellite Imagery in order to complete the gaps hinted at in this story.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;This project was supported by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://library.harvard.edu/grants-fellowships/pforzheimer-fellowships&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Pforzheimer Fellowship&lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA; at Harvard, with a focus on Geospatial Data and Archival Research, and overseen by the Map Collections and especially Belle Lipton.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Every good story starts with a spark and a helping hand to fan it. This one stems from the records and institutional knowledge unveiled by the wonderful people at Havard’s Map Collection. Custodians of many important maps and the personal documents of geographers having worked at Harvard, our Map librarians have kept a finger on the pulse of Geography’s unravelling at Harvard and beyond. Due to their unrestrained support, I was brought in contact in the very beginning of my Pforzheimer Fellowship with four inestimable pillars of the HUIGE’s story:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
