<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Georeferencing on GIS, maps &#43; data @ Harvard Library</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tutorials/georeferencing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Georeferencing on GIS, maps &#43; data @ Harvard Library</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tutorials/georeferencing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Georeference in QGIS</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/tutorials/georeferencing/qgis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/tutorials/georeferencing/qgis/</guid>
      <description>Download QGIS , if you haven&amp;rsquo;t already.&#xA;Add a basemap Browser → XYZ Tiles → Open Street Map.&#xA;Set the project coordinate reference system to WGS 84. At all times in the bottom right of the QGIS document, EPSG should read 4326.&#xA;Optional context on coordinate reference systems Every dataset and every QGIS project each has a coordinate reference system (CRS). Coordinate reference systems allow the GIS software to know where on the world to place the dataset, how to line it up spatially.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Georeference Harvard Library digital collections using Allmaps</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/tutorials/georeferencing/allmaps/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/tutorials/georeferencing/allmaps/</guid>
      <description>Topics covered by this guide Select a map to georeference from the Harvard Libraries&amp;rsquo; digital collections Georeference with free browser tool, AllMaps Add the georeferenced map to a GIS project in QGIS Select a map to georeference from the Harvard Libraries&amp;rsquo; digital collections If you visit the Harvard Library catalog, HOLLIS , you can: Change the initial search drop-down from Catalog &amp;amp; Articles to Library Catalog to show only items held by the library, and exclude journal articles.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Georeference in ArcGIS Pro</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/tutorials/georeferencing/arcgis-pro/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/tutorials/georeferencing/arcgis-pro/</guid>
      <description>Open a new map in ArcGIS Pro and select the basemap of your choice Map → Basemap → Open Street Map Set the projection by right clicking the basemap in the Contents pane and select Properties Properties → Coordinate Systems&#xA;Open the image which needs to be georeferenced Catalog → Folders → Add Folder Connection Right click on &amp;lsquo;Folders&amp;rsquo; and navigate to the folder containing the map that needs to be georeferenced.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
