<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Case Study on GIS, maps &#43; data @ Harvard Library</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/case-study/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Case Study on GIS, maps &#43; data @ Harvard Library</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/case-study/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Mapping Land Use Change in the Sacramento San-Joaquin River Delta</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/adler-delta/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/adler-delta/</guid>
      <description>Early one August morning, I found myself donning borrowed fishing waders on the banks of a restored tidal wetland in Northern California. Thanks to a Salata Institute grant, I spent a week studying the Sacramento San-Joaquin River Delta alongside biometeorology experts. After exploring maps of the region through my assistantship with the Harvard Map Collection, I was incredibly grateful for the opportunity to traverse the landscape on foot, and prepare for my senior thesis on the science of these special ecosystems.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Undoing Empire, One Plant at a Time</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/odessa-biodiversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/odessa-biodiversity/</guid>
      <description>Floral motif from Ukrainian textile produced in 1902.&#xA;This year, the Harvard Map Collection partnered with Kelly O&amp;rsquo;Neill from the Davis Center on a project to demonstrate the value of our GIS data curation services . Dr. O&amp;rsquo;Neill&amp;rsquo;s project aims to capture data about historic biodiversity in the Ukraine. The Harvard Map Collection worked with her team to co-develop robust and useful metadata, so that the sources can be archived for long-term discovery and reuse.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>City Fictions</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/city-fictions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/city-fictions/</guid>
      <description>This semester, we worked with Tara K. Menon&amp;rsquo;s English class, titled City Fictions. In this class, undergraduates explored the various ways writers capture the constituent features of life in urban environments, reading books set in London, Bombay, New York, and Tokyo.&#xA;Wonderground map of the London town, 1914. We were happy to learn that one of the course assignments involved mapmaking; in order to get at different ways the experience of city might be represented, students were tasked with creating two distinct maps of the same place.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
